welcome to untangling the world knot of
consciousness
wrestling with the hard problems of mind
and meaning in the modern scientific age
my name is john verviki i'm a cognitive
psychologist and cognitive scientist at
the university of toronto in canada
throughout the entire series i will be
joined in dialogue by my good friend and
colleague
greg enriquez from james madison
university in the united states
throughout we are going to wrestle with
the hard problems of how we can give an
account
of a phenomenal like consciousness
within
the scientific worldview how we can
wrestle with that problem in conjunction
with the problem that greg calls the
problem of psychology
that is pervasive throughout psychology
which is that psychology has no unified
descriptive metaphysics
by which it talks about mind and or
behavior
throughout this we will be talking about
some of the most important philosophical
cognitive scientific and neuroscientific
accounts of consciousness
so i hope you'll join us throughout and
we're going to
move into another stage of the argument
and start to consider
some actual current theories about the
nature
of consciousness so welcome greg as
always it's a pleasure to have you here
thank you so much yeah you know we we
got to a really important point about
adjectival and adverbial consciousness i
think we set up some
really interesting things i look forward
to bridging into those and
i'm excited about what we got coming
today great
so greg mentioned some of the things
let's just do a quick review
uh we took a look at how descartes uh
didn't solve but try at least gave good
strong indication
as to um how one could begin to follow
up on the intuition that the function
question
what does consciousness do and the
nature question
how does consciousness fit into the
furniture of the universe
because it's such a strange thing how
those questions could be
answered in an integrated fashion and we
look
we took a look at his idea uh of
pursuing a a relationship between
consciousness and intelligence
and we noted that that's a very powerful
intuition and it's a very powerful
intuition
um that speaks on behalf of
trying to answer the nature and the
function questions
in integrated fashion and what we can
what descartes proposed was that uh
animals that are intelligent without
conscious consciousness
have co-variations they have brain
states that covariate with the world
gives them a general and uh a general
capacity to
move around the world navigate the world
we then noted
that many theory current theories of
representation in fact
are covariation theories that a mental
representation is something in the head
that covaries with uh the world or
sometimes in the head and body et cetera
um but many people note within that
tradition that covariation doesn't have
the specificity of reference that mental
representations have
um and that descartes seems to have been
aware of this
not using those terms but something
analogous and it looks like what
consciousness does
is out of all of the things
that all of all the aspects
of co-variation is object
weapon black thing phone birthday gift
etc etc etc curtain
[Laughter]
what consciousness does is it
aspectulizes it picks out one of those
uh picks up one of those aspects and
readies it for reason readies it for
intelligent
uh behavior we we then noted by making
use of an argument from john cyril
uh that how deeply that aspect
realization and consciousness are
bound together representation
presupposes aspect realization
um and then cyril says that as
specialization presupposes consciousness
i propose to you that we could flip it
around that aspect realization
presupposes relevance realization
and relevance realization could be used
to explain in an integrated fashion both
intelligence
and consciousness via the function
of aspectualization yep
and then we took a look at what that
might look like uh if we took a look at
i mean
how about let me pause you right there
for just a second because okay because
this
readiness for reason i think is this
really really important
point and uh especially because we have
rene descartes doing this in
relationship to his own
human thinking uh what i would say
reading it for
mine three that rational justifying
right
but we're in the animal kingdom okay so
essentially it's
priming it uh in some ways to be we
don't mean reason in relationship to
justifying proposition but we do mean
holding it and perhaps simulating
various counter factual
scenarios uh and in my language then
calculating various paths of behavioral
investment uh for affordances and
stressors so now you get a
cortex that actually can really start to
integrate and simulate
if you want to connect it to brain-based
uh stuff so we can imagine how that
aspectualizing pulls in and then allows
mental manipulation in a particular kind
of way
right good excellent and so
uh we took a look at how that
functionality
uh uh might be related to our
phenomenological experience
and we took a look at michael palania's
work
um that is very much a case of i would
argue how such
a specialization occurs and we took a
look at
attention being something that bridges
between two two kinds of awareness
subsidiary awareness which is awareness
through
and focal awareness which is awareness
of and
that's you know that foregrounds things
the background we talked about the way
you know the the features in the gestalt
are related so
that's the whole aspectualization
process um
and then we took a look at you know
the rudiments of that uh in multiple
object tracking and the basic
salience tagging um and the work of zen
and pollution around this
and then we got the distinction between
adjectival folia
which tend to dominate the discussion in
consciousness the blueness of something
the
greenness versus the adverbial qualia
uh which is the here now-ness
togetherness um
which is which are the only qualia that
survive
when you uh load up multiple object
tracking
that's experimentally right replicated
and the idea that consciousness the
fundamental
act of the formulating act the act uh
the pro
the primordial act of aspect realization
is something
analogous to demonstrative reference
this
this this and the grouping of them
together that makes
and you need that for categorization you
can see
the getting it ready for what what they
are called reason
what you call right counter factual
thought yes
very much right i was just happened to
see a you know cool video on zip's law
uh i don't know if you know about that
but pareto distribution all that other
stuff but
it was on language okay and the most
common words
uh on the of and all of that
okay so all of those actually words are
finsta words
they basically are words that then are
going to reference where things
are rather than what they are
adjectivally you know the nouns verbs
express
so i was just it brought my to my
attention how
frequently our language is framing
finsta
kinds of emotions yeah exactly that's
good greg i didn't know about that
so the idea is you can see
aspectualization
making ready for you know higher
higher thought not full-blown reason i
grant you that
but something more uh in this act of
right we we we salience tag things we
have the business and the business and
and then a togetherness i hear now this
togetherness
and then that is what is needed in order
to
form a category and therefore to form
a concept so one way we might talk about
this
is a spectralization is um
transforming variations into
things that are ready for
conceptualization i was thinking about
saying full-blown uh reasoning might not
be right but something like
at least the beginnings of of
conceptualization
so we took a look at all of that and
that and then we we talked about the
fact that
in the pure consciousness event people
lose all the adjective polio
and all that's left is right a very
heightened
version of the hereness and the
noun-ness and the togetherness
the the sort of the here now eternity
and the togetherness is pure oneness
pure unity
and so you get kind of like this
gonzfeld
of just purely adverbial uh
qualia which is a good argument that
uh adverbial qualia are uh sufficient
uh for uh consciousness um
and that adjective folia are not
necessary
for for for consciousness i want to play
with this a little bit more
um in that um you could conceive of the
opposite
you could conceive of a creature kind of
a human monster
that had only adjectival qualia
disconnected not capable of being in any
way conceptualized
patches with the av patches blobs of
hereness sorry a blueness and greenness
that share no fearness
no nowness no togetherness is
that consciousness uh so i've regularly
reliably have done this with many people
and generally most people's intuition
quite strongly is no that doesn't
seem like consciousness anymore now
that's not as strong an argument as the
multiple object tracking argument
but at least is a plausible argument
that adjective folia
are right not sufficient for
consciousness
certainly not the way we fully think of
phenomenology right yeah so we have the
full phenomena
when you say oh i wake up okay i'm
asleep i'm unconscious i wake up
there's that there is they're both what
you're seeing in the witnessing function
that's pulling them together and
organizing yeah
and if you pull that off and said okay
all you had is some felt
sense um of adjectival
you know whatever right it's hard to
even imagine without the framing but you
can and actually i do believe my my
intuition and i think there's some
you know it's a hard problem but like
pleasure and pain
yeah a sort of root qualia that send out
that being to
move you know lean toward lean away
right
as sort of the elements of this uh the
very early
sentient you know the the hinting early
sentience
that then is going to be witnessed uh by
uh higher order processes that really
bring phenomenology together
feels to me like the way in which it
might have evolved
yeah that's that's a good expect that's
a good speculation like to come back to
that
i'll share one that i have so i have i
have less confidence in what i'm about
to say
it's much more speculative in the
pejorative sense of the word
i have a i have a speculation that
adjectival qualia
might be might be the instantiation
of that function whereby the where
whereby
the what's been made right like it's the
making ready for conceptualization
function
you have the spectralized function of
like of the hereness now in this
togetherness the demonstrative reference
analog and then you have something that
is actually making it ready
to be something like propositional
content or conceptual content
categorical content and i suspect that
adjective qualia might be
serving that function i have no good
argument or empirical evidence for this
claim
so please note uh that's what what i
could i'll say about it right now
okay okay so we we went through all of
this and if we go through the
if we go through the multiple object
tracking the pure consciousness event
the human monster
we seem to get an argument that uh
everybody
are sufficient adjectives are
are not sufficient neither are they
necessary
and therefore that would sort of lead to
the conclusion that a verbiago qualia
are also necessary and sufficient
uh which means they would you know in a
in a
logically proper sense constitute
essential features
uh of consciousness um
i'll just say this is what when when i
first heard you make this it made me
very excited about it because i
i was trapped i think in the adjectival
qualia i mean they're so
salient but but you're looking through
the witness function you're looking
through roger title
right yeah and it is definitely the
joint of those
um and sort of the separation of them uh
really helped and then when i was like
well what is the
what is the foundational essence of my
when i talk about perspectival knowing
or
what i use called phenomenological
knowing i mean that was my general term
it's that witnessing function so that
that really sat for me and it shifted
my attention it saw the way i i saw how
i was seeing through the lens of my
understanding that shifted and then
i got right into the the witnessing
function and to me
um that that linked many different
things together and definitely
afforded some insight so thank you i
mean so
the idea then the proposal which will
need further argumentation and evidence
is that the the aspect realization
function
and the hearing as togetherness uh can
be
explained um in terms of relevance
realization
and recursive relevance realization and
that that
and since i've got independent arguments
published elsewhere
that this relevance realization is the
court of general intelligence that would
help explain
justify the intuition that there's deep
connections between general intelligence
and uh consciousness so there's a lot
that's promising about this
i wanna also be clear one more time i'm
not saying and i know you're not saying
greg
that adjective of qualia don't exist i'm
saying that
i've even offered a speculation that
i don't have that much confidence in but
i don't have any alternative to it
either
what i think the adjective of qualia
might be or might be doing
we are going to take a look at other
people's proposals of the adjective
qualia
we will not find many proposals about
the adverbial qualia
and that's going to be surprising
especially when we look at people trying
to address the function
right consciousness okay so there's a
lot to
there's a lot to keep a look on so this
brings us to two
sort of a decision point as you start
down the
the the enormous tree banyan tree of
trying to explain consciousness
um one of the key decision points is
okay are you going to try and build
consciousness out
of representational content
the content of representation or you may
or you could try to build consciousness
as i've been suggesting
out of the aspectualizing framing
function
that gives rise to representations those
are two options available
now uh the one i mentioned first
is uh far and away the predominant
uh uh uh way people try that's the
predominant choice that people make
uh within cognitive science uh in
philosophy
first of all i wanna make clear why i
think that is an intellectually
respectable thing to do
while at the same time putting it into a
frame that might call it into question
i want to argue that trying to
understand consciousness
in terms of representational content
makes
excellent cartesian sense if you're if
you're in a cartesian framework
remember we talked about how the mind is
basically reduced to its
representational function
um and consciousness is going to somehow
therefore
be a function of representation the mind
is a purely epistemic engine
it's all just about truth and con
and truth attaches to the content of our
representations
and then you'd say okay and then
descartes you know consciousness
we talked about this is where the mind
touches itself it's all that's left of
conformity
well how do representations touch each
other
sorry for sounding graphic uh well what
well the idea is
one representation takes another
representation as its content
so i can have meta representations i can
have recursive representation i can have
a representation
about a representation in fact most of
our representations
are representations of representations
right
so the idea that many people have is
you'll build consciousness out of this
meta representational or this recursive
depending on whether you want to talk
about it structurally
or dynamically right this recursive
meta representational function now you
you're going to fit and this seems so
intuitive because consciousness feels
like it's
like it's always consciousness of some
states
that are representational nature so it's
a lot of intuitive plausibility it makes
terrific sense within the cartesian
framework of the mind
we've noted though that and then and
that cartesian framework
is massively legitimized by how it is
insinuated seamlessly
uh with the scientific worldview and
we've already given that argument
at length so
what greg and i also explored though is
that framework the cartesian framework
is tremendously problematic
it has it gives you the mind brain mind
body problem
it ramifies through the problem of
psychology it right
so our attempts to even get a science of
the mind going are undermined
by it all kind of so it's very
problematic so on what so i'm trying to
be very fair
to people here right i respect it makes
good sense
that within the cartesian framework you
would
try to build consciousness out of meta
representations
but we should also be suspicious of that
it's it's plausible it's
intellectually respectable but the
suspicion of it
should also be in our mind because that
whole framework is in some way
causing us a lot of deep and profound
problems
about the nature of mind and the nature
of ourselves
within the scientific worldview so how's
that located that sounds
right on right on par target with me so
yes
let's let's get into that that sounds
good so
i wanted i i so we do not have the time
or i think between even between us their
relevant expertise to cover
every single version of this theory
that's been promoted
so what i have chosen to do is to pick
one version of this theory that is
seminal in that it has influenced many
it's it's it's still it is
intellectually respectable in its own
right
and it's seminal also in the sense that
it inseminates many other
uh theories uh about consciousness and
this is rosenthal's
theory which is known as the higher
order thought
right or uh theory well or hot theory so
it's got a sexy mind right
yeah um i want that theory
uh so there's sort of four
conditions to this theory um the first
three
are unproblematic uh because it's the
fourth that is dealing with the problem
i've mentioned
okay uh so sorry the problem i'm gonna
bring up right away
so before i get into rosenthal's theory
what's the basic
problem for any matter representational
theory
of consciousness now this is a problem
not faced by descartes but it's faced by
all of us because we have the idea that
a lot of processing and we discussed
this last week with cyril
sorry last time was searle a lot of
processing
is unconscious cognitive processing and
that's presupposed
through most of cognitive psychology in
cognitive science okay
so the problem is
when you're going to explain
consciousness in terms of
representation you have to acknowledge
the fact that we have many
unconscious representations we have many
processes
using unconscious representations and
many of those
unconscious processes are
meta-representational in nature
right so i until i speak it
right i have an unconscious belief
that cats are mammals so i have a
representation cat
and part of its content is the
representation mammal
cat and mammal are not the same thing so
these are distinct representations
right right something can be a mammal
and not be a cat
for example okay so what i have is i
have here's an unconscious
representation
here's a higher order right there's a
representation that takes this
as its content so that if
right so that there's all kinds of
processing going on
uh in my memory reconstructive memory
might be doing something about my memory
of cats and its relationship
to other mammals via the connection we
know all kinds of stuff's going on
okay so you have lots of let's take it
that we have good empirical evidence
and i think pretty readily available
very much behavioral evidence
that we have unconscious meta
representations
and meta-representational processes
great let me let me pause you right
there for just a sec
okay so that people so to me one of the
things you
that that you you made a point about
well descartes sort of has this but he
doesn't
okay and and for me the issue is why
does it become
reified well it becomes reified through
the cybernetic and cognitive revolution
okay where now we have the concept of in
you know
information processing and
representation which we can now
ontologically map in artificial
intelligence and we all
and then it's like oh a system can
translate something it can get recursive
loops
it can make predictions based on
uncertainty reduction and we can build
systems this way so now
we have as part of our sense-making
architecture
right the concept of cognition broadly
defined
okay and that's a new idea
which is going to connect in my
estimation it's going to connect both to
well how do like robots behave and how
do you actually coordinate behavior
and it's going to connect to
consciousness but consciousness is also
going to get entangled well what do we
mean by
phenomenological consciousness right
yeah what you're articulating here is
well okay
representation on top of representation
but actually the cognitive both
helps with that or that concept but it
also obscures it because that can happen
without consciousness thank you very
much very much thank you very much
and in fact the that example uh greg a
great's point brings up a powerful
example and how this ramifies
into the function question which is it
will
we and you know we'll come back to this
when we do the chinese room and
versions of that things like that but
the idea that
we may get very sophisticated machines
um that are doing highly intelligent
behavior without consciousness
and then we remember that we now that we
can explain that behavior we
we are capable of understanding
ourselves as doing
so much that's intelligent without it
being
conscious and so this now again brings
up what is consciousness
for what does it do so you see how the
nature and the function questions
keep bouncing off of each other because
rosenthal is not
giving us a functional account he's
trying to give us an answer to the
nature
nature okay so let's so the issue is
how do you turn unconscious
representations
into into conscious representations
and and somebody might be saying that
sounds like the descartes problem of
co-variations into representation
i think there's similarity there we'll
come back to that so that's a good
thought
but let's come back to rosenthal's line
so how do i turn unconscious
representations
into conscious representations the
intuition is
i use matter representation the problem
is we have overwhelming evidence
that you can have meta representation
and media representational processing
without there being consciousness so
what does rosenthal say okay so let's do
it so the idea is
the first condition is i'm in some i
mean some i have some
unconscious representational state let's
call that
a here it is here represented by my
right foot okay
and then i have a another
unconscious representational state right
let's call this t because it'll be the
thought
of a right and we'll come back to what
that thought meet what flat means but
t is of a okay
and then the third condition is being in
a
causes being in t of a so if i have
this state it is causal of me
having this state is that okay does that
work so far
that works okay uh and we can note that
the nervous system is hierarchically
arranged definitely right so this idea
that this would be
hierarchical levels that's fine yep
that's fine
so the problem is as we said we've
already got good argument that that
is not sufficient for turning we have
counter examples we have lots of this
without there being consciousness so the
fourth condition which i call the
intimacy condition
and i can't remember greg if i came up
with that way of calling it or if i got
it from somebody else who called it that
because it's what it's all i have is
this meta memory
yes call it the intimacy did i did i
come up with that
or did i pick that up from somebody if
so i public thing if somebody else
came up with that designation and it's
and it's
right and it's extant in the literature
apologies right
and if they have it then let's use it
because it's act
so the intimacy condition is this idea
that a
causes t of a without there being any
inferential relationship
between a and t of a or there being any
sensory information passing between a
and t of a so what that means is
that there is no epistemic relationship
between a
and t of a it can't it doesn't come
through any kind of sensory information
or inferential information why well
because
uh rosenthal wants to block
blocking the inferential blocks the
examples i just gave of cat and mammal
right there's right it blocks that
relationship
so he says no that's not going to count
because the relationship between
a and t of a is non-inferential
he also wants to block weird
weird connections that loop through
sensory
um so let's use for example pain
let's say pain is uh
the a as there's a tissue damage
and then there is the recognition of the
need to
react to respond to tissue damage and
that right
okay so let's say my tissue is
damaged but i'm not feeling any pain and
then
i look and see blood right and that
sensory information
makes me behave in a certain way such
that i i pull away no notice my
avoidance
okay because i don't like the sight of
blood
does that mean i'm now in pain so the
idea is
no it's quite possible that i have the a
i have a t of a i don't like the sight
of blood
that's right and so i pull away
but that doesn't that's not the same
thing as feeling the pain of the cut
right right and so the idea here is you
want to block
those kinds of counter examples as well
you want you want it to be that and
here's the point
that there's some intimate connection
between
a and t of a it's not
mediated by inferential states it's not
mediated by sensorial states of of any
kind
is that okay so far that's okay so far
i'm following that
okay so the the of course the the
sixty four thousand dollar question now
is uh oh sorry that's our that's out of
date for people when i was growing up
it was a game called the 64 thousand
dollar question right the
the the winning the game 64 000
isn't very much anymore um um won't even
might buy it's not even a terribly
expensive car anymore
anyways uh so the question then comes
well if it's not inferential
and it's not via sensory information
what's the nation that's the nature of
the causal relationship
so let's grant the intimacy condition
that's correct because if we don't grant
it
then rosenthal series is just going to
be counter-exampled to death
so the key is that relationship
now that's a little bit trickier
about what it is so we have to get at
that more indirectly
and what i want to do is i want to take
a look at
uh two criticisms made by dretzki
of rosenthal theories two attempts to
refute it and then defenses
of rosenthal given by senior because
they will help
clarify what that intimacy condition
is okay so
rose uh betsy uses the example of pain
but
pain is somewhat problematic for people
um
in terms i don't mean that it exists or
that it's qualia
i mean uh of people's ability to sort of
parse it phenomenologically
um so i use this example which is
generally
better for people okay so i'm going to
slightly modify
this is just a pedagogical move there's
nothing substantial to it i'm just going
to slightly modify
fretsky's example and bring it up so
dretzki says
well uh this has happened to me
um i'm angry
right and it's clearly a a state that
i'm in uh
but i'm not aware that i'm angry
so if you'll allow me my language
i'm angry adverbially so right
i'm not aware of my anger i'm aware
through my anger of the world the light
the anger is the lens through which i'm
seeing things it's coloring things in a
certain way
you seem particularly threatening to me
right etc
you know you're hyper salient there's
like you know i'm getting aroused for
fighting you and all that's
all that sort of stuff but if you were
to ask me at that moment
or perhaps until you asked me are you
angry i don't i'm sure you encounter
this in therapy all the time
right that might that must happen all
the time to you right absolutely
okay so yes so the example is not
controversial
and then dretzki says well look what we
have here right
you know we have a
but we don't have t of a the person's
angry
but they're not aware that they're angry
and yet they're still conscious
that that anger is still a conscious
state
okay now first of all notice what's
happening here notice
how this is and and how i could
helpfully explain dretski by shifting
over to the adverbial
and looking awareness through not just
awareness of
so the language we've introduced is
already helpful
for explicating dretzki's point but
steven comes back and says no no no
that's a mistake
that's a deep mistake okay and and it's
it's it's really interesting greg how
often and when i'm teaching this
argument people make this mistake even
after i've taught them the mistake
okay so a is
unconscious in rosenthal's model and so
is
t of a right
right dretzki
is identifying t of a
with the introspective awareness of a
right so and that right that's
not we've got to go really slowly here
that's not what roger's all saying
for rosenthal both a and t of a are
unconscious
it's only in the intimacy condition that
the joint
the composite of the two achieves
consciousness
right now so t of a
is not your introspective awareness of
your mental states
right so a way of putting that that
might make it easier for people to grasp
and this is the distinction that is
important there's a big difference
between being
conscious and being self-conscious
right there's one more clarification
there's two meanings of self-conscious
one is consciousness of yourself and one
is reflective
reflexive consciousness i mean the
latter not the former we'll talk about
the former later on
okay so there's a difference between
me being angry and me and be being aware
that i'm angry between being conscious
and being self-conscious in
introspection
introspection is the function which by
which i become
self-conscious of my conscious states
is that okay right and so yeah i'll just
jump this is
in my language system we're talking
about uh you want to layer this up
mind one which is the neurocognitive
functionalism
okay and then into mind two which is
going to be i think
a on to t but that's different from mine
three
okay which is the self-conscious
recursive introspection awareness that
can report
on all of that process exactly exactly
right uh you inverted it by the way it's
t of a not amt but that's
but i'm inverted for you so i get why
that happens
um so we so the
higher order thought t
of a is not it it is not itself a
conscious state
you have an unconscious state and an
unconscious state
and when they are in the intimacy
relation that
the the composite is a conscious state
so we shouldn't confuse
right the higher order thought with
conscious introspection that is a
mistake good okay
so so let me see if i'm following this
okay so
i think we talked about the duck rabbit
uh illusion last time
right so at one liara you're bringing up
the a
and then you have contact with either a
duck or a rabbit
right right right okay so then you'd
have the phenomenological experience
and that's so when you see the duck
there is the contact
there right and then when you see a
rabbit there's the contact there
right and then that's different also
than with the hey what is that like for
you when you think about that
yes yes exactly exactly exactly
because presumably animal many animals
will probably have the first and lack
the second i think there's a game
changer with language on that uh
yes and for example just to be clear
there seems to be very good uh
developmental empirical
evidence experimentally based and also
case study based
that children are incapable of
introspection
until they're about four years of age
even though they are
clearly conscious now in fact i
being the weird weird cognitive
scientist i am i
actually recorded the first instances
that were clear
instances of my younger son being
introspective because when he was you
know
two to four kids have language actually
no that's quite sophisticated that's
right you can ask them what's going on
in their head and they'll say things
like blood
or or right
my younger son he uh we were driving
along in the car he was in the back seat
he was just coming into four
uh around there and he said oh it's
snowing
but not outside only in my head
right and then there was another one
when he came up to me
and he said i have a reverse camera in
my head
and i'm thinking what what does that
mean
and he said and and and i asked him
he was getting the and this we know that
this also takes language
he was getting auto auto noetic memory
he was capable of time travel
he was capable of reversing and going
back into the pounds
interestingly uh just as an anecdote a
side note i should say
i asked him does anybody else have the
reverse camera
oh no no
no no way man this is
okay so let's remember to
and this is a general lesson this is why
i introduce it we've got to keep it
throughout
that we shouldn't confuse a couple of
things we shouldn't
confuse focal awareness with subsidiary
awareness
we shouldn't confuse consciousness
with introspective self-consciousness we
have to keep
all this thing right and people slam
these all together absolutely that's why
that's why mine three self-contact
introspection is so different than mine
too
and if we don't have the right language
systems you know then you would say no
animals aren't conscious well if you
mean they're not great at self-conscious
retrospection and self-report
yeah yeah but do they feel pain and have
uh a to t experiences you know yeah
that's right
that's right okay so i think that's very
very useful
um uh just again
so clarifying clarifying clarifying
but notice what we're doing is all of
these
um this all these explications of
distinctions all these distinctions
are each time we do this we are gaining
the
increase in clarity because we are
reliably and systematically reducing
the potential for equivocation this is
not niggling
we have to do this correctly or we will
get it we will get it wrong right we'll
get it wrong
okay now the second argument by dredski
against rosenthal is a little bit more
uh
interesting in terms of but it tells us
more about what that
intimacy condition might be
so uh dretzki says okay well
if you're doing this t of a what
what that means is that all
consciousness is consciousness ads
it's all when you and you we've already
did this you did uh wittgenstein's
duck rabbit all seeing is seeing as
seeing it as a duck or seeing it as a
rabbit
all consciousness is consciousness as
which of course is
guess what ass spectralization so as
specialization
bang back on the table again without
being properly exploited
without being foreground without the
discussion of adverbial qualia
or all of this but it's here it's going
to take a central role
and then dretzki says okay so if
rosenthal is right
then right every conscious state
is going to be aspectualized
and then he argues and says but
there doesn't seem to be any aspect
that's necessary
to in any state of consciousness and
so let's use i could i could be
conscious of it as a duck
as a rabbit as a black and white blob
as a smear as the thing that greg often
refers to
right no one so and then jessica says
but look
none of these aspects are necessary
and then he concludes so
aspectualization is not necessary
and since rosenthal is committed to a
specialization
i have thereby refuted his theory and
senior points out that's a modal fallacy
the fact that no one particular aspect
is necessary that you cannot conclude
from that
that no aspect is necessary let me give
you an example
okay i'm talking about bodies not matter
bodies
okay is everybody clear about that so
every body i encounter has a shape
but is any particular shape necessary to
being a body like do you have to be a
rectangle to be a body
nope do you have to be a sphere you have
to be there is no
shape that's necessary but does that
lead me to the conclusion
that shape is not a necessary feature of
being a body
that's a moral mistake the fact that
each one
might be individually not necessary does
not lead to the conclusion
that the entire set can be excellent
okay
a category right exactly now notice what
that shows you
it shows you first of all that
aspectualization
really can't be separated from
consciousness and secondly
it's the process of actual
spectralization
not the specific aspect that is actually
central
to consciousness it derives us this is a
completely independent argument
right but it leads to the same
conclusion
that the process not the not a
particular set of attributes
revealed by a particular aspect but it's
the process of aspect realization itself
that's necessary to consciousness now
what i want to suggest to you is that we
should consider
the aspectualization process as exactly
the intimacy relation
that is needed that it turns right
unconscious co-variations
right into things ready to be mapped
into potentially unconscious concepts
the way we've been talking about and
that is the process
that is the intimacy intimacy condition
of consciousness why would i make that
argument well first of all we already
it's independently motivated it's
independently motivated by how
aspectualization has come to the fore
but it's also going to be motivated by a
second argument which
well let's take a look at while always
keeping the intimacy condition
clearly in hand let's take a look at
higher order thought theory what is
a thought i mean it's a really vague
term it's an equivalent
so one thing that you might
try is that higher order thoughts are
beliefs
higher order thoughts or beliefs so what
t is of a is t
is a belief about a so i'm in some
particular state
and then i get a belief about that state
and the belief about that state
um and what one of the advantages of
that is belief is
different from just conceptual
relationship
so that might give you a little bit of
wiggle room
the problem with that of course is we
have unconscious beliefs about our
beliefs
we already have that and they remain
unconscious uh
so and this points to a lot of the
differences between belief
and consciousness our beliefs don't seem
to be
processes that occur they seem to be
dispositions to behave this is a classic
argument made by gilbert raw
so until i spoke it i i i
i still believe it but until i spoke at
it right it was in no way
um conscious to me i believe that africa
is the continent
now i've had that belief all day
but that doesn't mean i've been thinking
it all day in the sense of
africa as a continent africa as a
continent africa's a continent
or doing like sorting things into
continents and putting africa into
like i've just i've been doing nothing
with africa incontinence all day
right and that nevertheless i have the
belief so what is it to have the belief
well i mean it's a very problematic
notion but it seems like it's
like if i have to categorize continents
i will put out
africa into the category if you ask me
this question i'll answer yeah
right and so beliefs aren't current
they're not happenings
they're conditional relations but
whatever the hell consciousness is
it is occurring it is a current thing
right yes absolutely
so one of the way you might get around
it is by saying well the belief isn't
the current
but this is occurring but then how
what the relationship between a
non-occurring state and occurring state
is such
that the overall result is occurring is
also
you know unclear but
you seem to be able to direct your
consciousness in a way that you can't
direct
your beliefs there's a voluntary aspect
of consciousness
and i don't need to belable this with
argument because there's a long-standing
tradition
of a deep association between
consciousness and free will
i'm not arguing for free will i'm not
claiming it exists
all i'm pointing to is there's something
about consciousness that leads people to
believe
consciousness is a self-moving free
thing your beliefs don't function that
way
belief is not something you do uh pick a
belief you'd like to have
i i would like i would like to have the
belief which
and to believe something is to believe
that it's true right i would i would
like to have the belief that everybody
loves me okay
okay let's do it let's do it now i'm
gonna start believing it
i can say it to myself everybody loves
me but i don't believe it
right uh i can imagine it i can imagine
all the people in the world
we love you john but i can imagine i
could desire it
i could fear it i can hope it but none
of those things are the same thing as
believing it belief doesn't work though
in fact i'm always
i'm always unclear what is supposed to
happen when televangelists
asked me to believe like believe
and i i feel like i i sort of clench
it's sort of like mental constipation i
sort of clench
what am i doing what like i don't know
what i'm supposed to be doing right
and what they're basically saying is
stop criticizing stop reflecting
and if you do all those things that will
then cause you to come to a state
of belief right um so all of that being
said
uh and there's more what i'm trying to
point out is belief doesn't
belief it's just not the right kind of
thing thing
yeah for consciousness so we we need
something that's much
more of a process
and that isn't some important sense you
know
self-organizing dynamic recursive
uh right and so i suggest
you that something that is occurring
definitely uh is
uh something that is self-organizing
and we already have independent
arguments that it converts
unconscious things into things
that are ready for
reason or ready for conceptualization of
bringing of an a
and a t of a together is the process of
aspect realization
the process of seeing through
co-variations
so that i now am aware of
a particular aspect of the world in a
way
that makes it ready poised for me to
entertain
concepts conceptual problem solving
about it
right and so i would propose to you that
what we're actually talking about in the
intimacy condition
is the process of aspectualization
yes so let me see how this uh sits with
you it's
as a metaphor sure okay so
um for me one of the things that i
sometimes use as a metaphor for
how the brain when sort of the basic
structure of the brain
is pulling its focus all right is like a
stadium
okay and each of the um
audience members each of the fans right
is tracking
a particular aspect of say the game
that's taking place
right right and there's a particular
frame that is
constraining and orienting the key
aspects
of change yes right okay and then
somehow the collective of that
okay is harmonizing so there are these
yeah where they're trying to
track the particular elements all right
so if we put this into a little bit of a
brain
model okay uh or at least and obviously
i'm being metaphorical here but
i want to be drawing the brain
connection right if there's some
if there's a frequency of the fans that
are tracking
okay they're tracking different aspects
all right
of change that are relevant right uh
then that's that that's a way to bring
the collective to map
the a to t it seems yes yes yes okay and
i'll go one step further if we then
bring this up into social psych with
this analogy
right what aspects of the game and how
are they actually being attended to and
indeed this will get into some mind
three justifying
you probably know this one of the
earliest examples of social psych and
perception
uh was they looked at a football game
that was particularly rough and brutal
okay they had two fans i think it's
dartmouth and princeton if memory serves
and they ask which which team was by far
the more
cheating aggressors in the game okay so
who were the dirty players
and who wasn't the dirty players right
well guess what all the princeton fans
said those dartmouth bastards they were
unbelievable
right and they had all these penalties
and our guys are just reacting and of
course you're flipping around
okay all right so so the so the frame of
aspectualization if we start to think
about
what frames of mind are people looking
through and how are they setting up
to see the co-variation across multiple
levels we can then start to see that
pull so i'm pulling the
the stadium idea of the brain into also
that's good let's pick up on that a
little bit that's helpful
uh so first of all again uh and greg's
done this before and i want to
uh bring it foreground it this
aspectualization
is a framing and it is a relevance
realization
and notice a couple of things so it's
and this is going to be down the road
i'm going to say that um you know
when the aspect realization is in
you know doing this reading for reason
reading for
but when the aspect realization actually
affords perspectival knowing
i think that's what's going to be
full-blown consciousness
and but notice what's happening also the
perspective of knowing
so you know uh it was was bound up
with the participatory knowing of the
observers
these one group of people have they
identify
right as dartmouth the other was it
plymouth or again
i think princeton i may be mistaken on
this but it doesn't matter no no it
doesn't matter
right so they're participatory knowing
the kind of identities they assume
and the kind of identities they assign
and the way
literally here the agent arena
relationship
i'm glad you picked up yeah i was like
so appreciate that
the participatory knowing right uh
uh it it shapes the framing
so that only certain kinds of
perspectival knowing
are are are sort of possible and then
that perspectival knowing
as greg said right it is constraining
the aspectualization so
only certain aspects are coming out
and that of course then affords what
skills
right people can be bring to bear and
what skills they can acquire within that
context
and that's the procedural knowing and no
and all of this
is happening um in ways
that seem to involve consciousness
before we get to that the the the
propositional
propositional narrative right but then
we would then nest them in layers of so
now
i say to my guy you know i'm there with
my buddy from dartmouth and did you see
that and he says of course i see that
now we have a shared collective
intelligence that those princeton guys
are this way and then we frame our
justifications which frames our
prospective knowing
which frames our projected participation
as fans into the system
so it's that constant you know we could
see that relation
across those various levels as to you
know as to how two
sides can watch the exact same game and
come across and of course as a
therapist i see this in marriage there
all the time in terms of like you know
oh my god is this
you know you hear one side like oh my
god how do they live with that person
you hear the other side like oh my god
how do you live with that person
right um so it's so just the nested
layers of
this aspectualizing uh across these
domains
is a very i think it's a very very
powerful thing to understand the dynamic
participatory relations that we are
engaged
i think that's fantastic um and
one of the ways of course you show the
value of a scientific theory
is not only its empirical adequacy how
can it explain the
consensus evidence and data um you also
write you one something that argues
for a theory i'm not claiming this a
full-blown scientific theory but
we're working towards it is the degree
to which it is fruitful the degree to
which it
bring make makes things clear that we're
not clear before
brings in new phenomena that could now
be considered relevant
evidence for the discussion of
consciousness uh that might
you know it's less likely without this
language
that we would consider things happening
in therapy
as particularly relevant to
understanding the nature and function of
consciousness but this language allows
us to bridge
allows us to see things happening um
within the therapeutic context as well
so notice where we've gotten to because
it's we're in a kind of a very
interesting place here
we we we we were playing it i'm sorry i
keep running with it we were playing in
the cartesian ball park
sorry there's a part of my mind
solid we're going to do it with you know
representational content of
representational content
we hit this you know really thick
problem
uh uh and so we put in the intimacy
condition
uh we try to get clear about what the
intimacy condition is and lo and behold
we find that right in terms of
responding
uh to uh criticisms by dredski
um and in terms of avoiding the things
that are prohibited
in the intimacy uh uh
condition uh we we find ourselves
zeroing in
on the process of a specialization
as actually the best candidate and
and i mean i i i i hope people aren't
feeling this like a sneaky ninja
uh jiu jitsu move or something
but as we in good faith i i it was a
good faith tried to pursue
this argument and the debate around it
we seem to have shifted to
maybe it's better to try and get
consciousness out of the process
of aspectualization rather than out of
the
content of our representations yes
absolutely and i think that what and
i'll just say also
i'm a i my you know they're different
models of truth of course there's
foundationalism there's correspondence
there's coherence whatever my genetic
system got lined up coherence
is certainly something i find myself
enormously
interested in and so for me when i get
really excited when i take something
it coheres with a lot and it applies
into these different domains
and it feels does so in a way that's
most parsimonious and starts to
create you know symphonic harmony
between different domains that
that is and so that's one of the reasons
i like this so much is because that's
what happened to me as i listened to
this through
i could then apply it network stuff
together across a wide variety of
generalities so for me
that truth criterion is a particularly
important one
so thank you for saying that craig
that's helpful i i also want to
return the favor and point out that greg
did something
uh very very smart uh
because the analogy is also a seed
analogy that analogy
is going we're going to ask you to
remember it remember the
the stadium analogy uh because it's a
version
of uh the analogy that's at the core of
bernard barr's theory called the global
workspace theory
uh which is one of the prominent uh
cognitive scientific
clear and there's a neuroscientific
version of it with the hain a cognitive
scientific and neuroscientific theory of
consciousness the global workspace
theory
um and it is a theory that is
just a foreshadow it's a theory that is
trying to answer the function
um the function question and it
explicitly
argues that the function of
consciousness
is relevance realization so again
that's a convergent argument that we're
going to be reaching towards
the relevance realization it also is
crucial in linking to working memory
which is crucial in
intelligence and problem solving and
consciousness
yeah we'll come back to that argument
that um
relevance realization seems to be very
crucial for working memory
especially the work of my colleague at
uft lynn hasher
and that working memory has a lot to do
with general intelligence as greg just
said
but of course there seems to be deep
connections between consciousness and
working memory especially
if consciousness gives us some capacity
for counterfactuality
but right uh and all kinds of things
like that
um what's interesting about all of this
is the connections
that we can make between consciousness
working memory
and general intelligence and between
different theories about the nature of
consciousness
working memory and intelligence so uh
so that's uh really really powerful and
if you're if one's intelligence like
mine orients towards coherence
all of a sudden you start seeing music
okay so that's
um that sort of got us to an interesting
place
and now that's going to bring up a
discussion
uh this another distinction uh in the
literature
um and uh we'll come back to it
it's a just and it's a it's a somewhat
controversial distinction
but it's a powerful one that many people
think
is um useful uh distinctions are
justified by their use
right because they have to do with
deciding the relative relevance of
things
so nedblock famously made a distinction
between access consciousness and
phenomenal consciousness
um and access consciousness
is basically that things are conscious
and again again i don't even know he's
aware of some of this historical
language
but access consciousness is when things
are poised
uh when there are mental contents
that are poised they have been readied
for reason
or what we're saying they've been
readied for this
more more more counter factual
intelligent behavioralization
yeah stimulation right
simulation yeah yeah oh sorry i said
simulation didn't i oh i heard
stimulation whatever
oh well i think i might have said it but
what was in my mind
was simulation okay uh and and
and greg and i will talk about how
that's probably an active simulation
rather than any kind of propositional or
pictorial or something like that
and we'll come back to that later so
some of you might be getting ah right
just wait
a fully embodied 4e version of
simulation is
what what we're going to argue for uh
and that's that's not that uncommon by
the way
so but that's down the road so let's get
back to what's going on with block
right and notice what we've got here
we've got this readiness for reason
and again well what does that look like
well it
he calls this access consciousness
because it's it's like you're bringing
things are being poised to be brought
into
working memory and used and what's a
good candidate for that well a good
candidate for that is
it's very processed we've been talking
about this aspectualization
this getting things ready right for
their categorical identity
all that stuff that we've been talking
about
in a related manner and they argue a lot
um i'm going to go a bit on
access consciousness before i go back to
phenomenal consciousness in a related
manner uh michael ty has argued for
um uh sort of a way of talking about
um uh consciousness um
and and he and and he and black seem to
argue around this point of poisonous
um and access and it it's not clear
if if it's a deep difference that the
rest of us should care about
or if it's the narcissism of small
differences so well welcome to
this is not primarily a scholastic
endeavor greg and i are
are engaged and so i'm going to put that
you know that intricacies aside i want
to
just briefly go over what ty says
so tai says that you know when we're
talking about
the the functional nature of conscious
we're talking about consciousness he has
what he calls
panic it's an acronym uh so
um what turns an unconscious state into
a conscious state
it's poised in the way we've just been
talking about
it's readied right it's it's go it's
it's
being i would argue or i think you would
argue with me
it's being the demonstrative reference
all that stuff's going on that's being
readied right for concept
categorization conceptualization
potentially counter factual simulation
etc all of that okay so
it's abstract now that's
going to be something we're going to
come back to uh you'll see why in a sec
all right it's non-conceptual
okay so it's non-conceptual it's
intentional content
okay so the difference between
unconscious con unconscious content
and conscious content is panna now of
course they both share
content so that falls out um the fact
that it it's intentional that's it's
about something
um that is
just to say that the content is in some
sense plausibly
representational or at least intentional
and again
the fact it's plausible that many people
would see
unconscious representations as having
that so
i don't think the i and the sea of panic
do
a lot of the distinguishing work they're
needed there because if you don't have
inc
the rest doesn't work so if you'll allow
me a bit of a greek pun
pan is doing all of the work uh
so poise get that man a mic
okay why is abstract non-conceptual
so the the the the problem with
abstract is non-cons it's the fact that
it's also non-conceptual
now we can talk about non-conceptual
because
we've got a non-conceptual thing going
on with all of the aspectualization and
the fence thing and the adverbial
right right all that stuff so
that's okay but normally when we talk
about
abstract we talk about something that is
higher on a taxonomic order
so vehicle is more abstract than car
which is more abstract than mustang
which is more abstract than my old
mustang
right right right and so i move up so
uh now but that taxonomies are precisely
conceptual structures
so what does non-conceptual abstractness
look like
so here is a proposal we can't get it
out of propositional content because
it's non-conceptual
so the abstractness has to be procedural
in nature
well what would procedural abstractness
means and here's where
i'm giving a proposal i think procedural
abstractness is generalizability
the degree to which i can apply
a procedure across a wider diversity of
context
is the degree to which it is
procedurally abstract
okay
and so what we need is a kind of
poisonous that is that kind of
generalized procedure
and what seems to be the one of the most
domain
general procedures of consciousness
well aspectualization aspectualization
no matter where we go if i'm going to do
any particular representational content
i first have to do the aspectualization
that will get me into the place in which
the conceptualization can then occur
so i think that
access consciousness like just again
making a convergent argument
um block and from time can be understood
again
in this very general process which
i think is a instantiation of
the what i think is one of the most
procedurally general things we have
which is our capacity for relevance
realization
all right all right so what i'm giving
is a convergent
argument that access consciousness is
basically doing this aspectualization
function this higher order relevance
realization
what i'm going to argue in fact is
aspectualization is basically
right and we already did it with the the
salience tagging
um relevance is becoming salient
where salience is relevant to
either if you want to talk structurally
relevance
to working memory or we want to talk
functionally
it's uh relevance right
to this relevance within perspective
knowing
right so we're going to come back to all
of that
so uh and i'll say also so from a
behavioral
investment so i'm always so i'm
embedding this in the whole organism
that's why i love foreign
right and why i love relevance
realization
is because what does the organism need
to do to invest it needs to know what is
uh and what it might be able to create
to make
today right yeah so it is in the process
all the way through of like okay where
am i and what might be possible
as i invest and so that that dual sided
element of realization that you have
yeah yeah yeah right it's like okay i
got to detect what it is and then what i
what can i realize with it and that goes
so deep into this structure
right and and both of those stages hit
the problem of combinatorial explosion
but in and allow all the way down
through the scale in a fractal sort of
way as far as
yeah exactly exactly exactly
so i mean i have a lot more on this but
what i've tried to do is make plausible
the idea that
perhaps we should try and build
consciousness at least access
consciousness
uh out of aspectualization now what
about phenomenal consciousness
well phenomenal consciousness is the
home of the adjectival qualia
right um and if there's controversy
about what it is and what it might be
ned block has what he calls sort of a a
mental paint
uh analogy it's sort of a mental paint
that
attaches to things and it's irreducible
uh to conceptual content it's
irreducible to functionality
um uh like i said
it's if that mapping is correct that
sounds like adjectival qualia to me
and that means that it's not clear that
it's necessary
or sufficient for consciousness i also
worry
on the other end of making it completely
non-functional
makes it epi phenomenal yep which is
going to be very problematic
right so that's why i like to i do like
this
kind of idea a little bit uh and then i
love saw the
access blocks uh distinction here so uh
if we go back to what
you know my intuition at least is is
that
pleasure and pain are flashes of paint
across the nervous system yeah okay that
then that then
try to orient the whole brain approach a
void and that's and so that's the early
you know and then you know then it
spreads off of there and then you're
getting this access conscious witnessing
system that's good greg
let can we let's we got a couple minutes
let's play with that okay i mean
we should we should try and do a little
bit of the logos in the midst of all of
this right um
so let me play with that a little bit so
i mean
of course pain and pleasure are salients
or salience tigers but
your point is they're not just sailing
staggers things can be salient without
being painful
or pleasurable so i agree with you there
but but it's interesting because pain
and pleasure
right are are are less distinct which is
your point
they're they're they're procedurally
abstract in the way we've been talking
about
they generalize across many domains in a
way that
red and even red and greenness won't
generalize
and so maybe are are they part of
an initial procedural categorization
like
approach avoid right right so
wow it's neat because then it's getting
really right at the level between
sort of salience and the so if you'll
allow me sort of
uh proto uh adjective qualia right yes
it's right it's right in the right area
right exactly
is that what you're suggesting 100 so
right these are
nature signals to approach and avoid
their nature
signals to approach and avoid so so and
then
that then basically is a sort of like so
for me
what i call the pleasure pain parallel
fitness principle okay so
there's a positive and negative
correlation of energy investment
associated with survival and
reproductive security
sure and then you get embedded in that
as the
capacity for behavioral investment
repertoires get more and more
sophisticated more and more flexible
it goes from fixed action patterns and
reflexive withdrawal systems
to coordinated guidance towards
particular outcomes
that are much more flexible and then
feed back on your consequences
okay and then you get feedback on
consequences you then have
bing pleasure pain splashing across the
nervous system
okay and then a capacity to specialize
around that
and then all of a sudden be guided by
that increasingly sophisticated smart
ways
right that's cool so right
right so let me try and do this
phenomenologically you have like
you have some basic here now this
togetherness the adverbial thing and
you've got salience
and then what what what what's what i'm
sort of picturing in my mind
i don't even know this right is you get
sort of a specification of salience
right it's still not it's not sort of
located
it's not a property of an object yet
right like
to something being painful is not a
property of any
particular thing right it's just you see
what i'm
it's it's it's a specialization of
salience that
if there's a qualitative change there
that's interesting that's
interesting it's right on the order yeah
right well so the
so here's another way of framing it okay
so uh in terms of the dynamic feedback
loop
of what i would call the whole of
phenomenological knowing
okay which is going to be procedural
perspectival and participatory
right uh what i did is i constructed
what's called the pme
loop okay the pme is the perception
that's gonna then
create the aspect realization and the
integration will be higher up in the
animal kingdom of the integration of the
adjectival into at by adverbial so we're
now seen through we have them
and then that's referenced against your
motivational state of approach a void
right right right so now i have a i'm
hungry i want to eat this thing and i
want to avoid
being eaten over here right right right
so i have an approach template to eat
this
okay and then avoid template to eat that
to a bee
eaten by that so and just to even as i'm
like i'm camping i get hungry i know my
my uh sandwich is over there right so
then all of a sudden i'm like oh i'm
hungry i'm gonna then
organize my investment all right to
reduce the discrepancy between where i
am
and to make salient that path of
investment
as i do that and i get in there i found
oh here's the sandwich
that i want i get more and more pleasure
affect as i reduce the discrepancy
to my goal so i start getting the jolt
there that says reinforce and do more of
that
okay then all of a sudden i get a a bear
pops up
all right let's see a bear pops up now
all of a sudden i have an image
of getting eaten i'll have an idea that
the bear moving towards me
okay which then activates all sorts of
avoidance fear-based motivation
i back up and tail hightail it out of
the car right
so i'm in a dynamic relation between
constantly
creating perceptions referencing them
against goal states
and having jolts of emotion to energize
myself accordingly
okay so let's pick up on that that's
good let's go to the other end though
let's do the pair of music the
paramecium approaches and avoids
but i'm not quite sure we could
attribute pain and pleasure to it
and here's the difference because it
came out in your example
because you did that you know you did
the the improvement
of optimal grip the reduction of the
discrepancy
because pain and pleasure are a
specification of salience across
time that affords learning right and so
that it right again we're bringing in
intelligence so
pain and pleasure then like like i said
i i i hadn't thought about this
but your point is really cool they're
they're fascinating they're they sort of
hover between adjectival and adverbial
folia
right and what they're doing is they're
opening up salience
to being specified across time so that
learning and flexibility
flexible response is possible is that a
fair representation
absolutely i also think that they sit
right in that weird space of realization
that they're detecting what is and
orienting what ought to be so that they
have that energy
to create really i mean we as lived
organisms we
sit in a nest of is on right yeah yeah
you know
you have to do that and so i see it as
that
it yolks that stuff together across the
you know
that's fantastic well that was all
that was all the content the pun
intended that i wanted to uh
get across uh for today um i think we
made some excellent
progress um uh
what what did we do well we saw that the
higher order theories seem to
converge back towards aspectualization
and then we've talked about you know how
that also now involves
shifting from relevance to salience and
then we did some
a discussion about uh access versus
phenomenal
and again we seemed to get right we seem
to really thicken up access so it did a
lot of the work that
is usually attributed to phenomenal
consciousness
and then we did something really
interesting we speculated about
sort of um the emergence
of adjective qualia out of adverbial
processing
via uh you know pain and pleasure
and how they seem to be well at least at
least
right now this sort of specification of
salience
across time that affords learning and
the improvement
of behavior and so that that that has
all been
uh i think tremendously uh fruitful and
uh and wonderful so uh thank you very
much again greg thank you very much
uh that man thanks for watching that
last move
that last move with pain and pleasure
thank you for bringing that in i hadn't
brought that in
to my thinking before that was very very
very very insightful very helpful so
thank you very much
happy to do so man uh the the split
between adjectival as you know in
adverbial so if we
uh we can harmonize and create coherence
well that's what dlo goes and all this
is all about right that's right
okay i'm gonna uh wrap us up for today
and we'll see all of you next time on
the
the next meeting on untangling the world
nod of consciousness
take care everyone